hey guys Shan side welcome to concept
and coding and today we are going to see
the spring boot jpa part one and let's
start without wasting any time so here
if you see that till now whatever we
have done it's mostly a part of
application logic now we have reached to
a stage where we have to insert data
into the database how we can do that so
that's where the jpa jdbc comes into the
picture Okay so before even jumping into
the jpa we have to first understand the
complete sequence right who who what all
components actually get involved into
this so here if you see that let's say
that you are writing a spring boot
application you have an application
logic or you have written so many beans
okay now what you do is if you have to
use jpa what's the sequence what happen
is you interact with an
apis which is provided by jpa so always
remember that jpa is mostly an interface
right it provided a apis which you can
interact with but it do not provide you
the implementation implementation is
provided by another component let's say
in this case hibernate or if you don't
want to use hibernate there is something
like open
jpa right or there I think Eclipse link
and uh so these are different
implementation of jpa okay so your
application talks to jpa jpa internally
has to be implemented by some other uh
component which you decide which you
want to use so generally hibernate is
the most popular one so hibernate
internally talks to or utilize
jdbc API so again jdbc is again and
interface so hiet uses
its API it's
interfaces and then there are specific
DB drivers so this DB drivers is nothing
but an implementation of this jdbc apis
okay so for example you are using
a MySQL DB okay you are using a MySQL DB
then there would be a specific DB driver
for it okay let's say it
is connector J DB driver which is very
very specific for MySQL which knows how
to connect to mySQL and it provided the
implementation of jdbc API similarly if
you have something called uh
postgress postgress SQL okay then it has
its own DB
driver it has its own DB
driver okay so depending upon which DB
you are using a specific that's why I
written a specific DB driver is required
okay this DB drivers is nothing but an
implementation of jdbc apis this jdbc
right uh Java database conect uh
connectivity helps you to connect to a
database okay through this API you can
connect you can query you can fetch the
data okay but remember jdb jdbc is
nothing but an
API interface actual work is done by
drivers itself if you using MySQL then
MySQL drivers know how to F the data
okay then this jdbc now there is
something called or framework is buildup
object relational mapping framework so
this is nothing but a
bridge
between Java
object and your
relational databases
okay so here if you see that in the jdbc
and specific DB driver everything we are
in the form of SQL right we write
queries and we try to connect uh through
DB create DB or F the data insert
everything is in SQL
form but here with the OM framework
where this jpa and let's say its
implementation hiate we are using if
this comes into the picture we don't
have to your application don't have to
directly work with the jdbc apis you
don't have to write SQL queries to
insert you can directly work with Java
objects
itself okay through Java objects itself
you can maintain your relational
databases so remember jpa jdbc is just
for maintaining relational databases so
before going to jpa Let's recall
jdbc Java database connectivity
okay so here if you see that it provide
an interface to make connection with DB
query DB and process the result whatever
the data we get out of DB we also have
to process it so it provide an API
through which we can process it and
implementation is provided by specific
DB drivers if you're using my SQL DB
then it has its specific drivers right
so likewise so here if you see my SQL
if you're using this DB what is the
driver connector J and this is the class
we have to load for it if you are using
postgress SQL this is the driver and
this is the class through which we can
load this driver similarly S2 which is
in memory relational database and its
driver is this one S2 database engine
and this is the class to load this
driver so this driver now anybody say
that what is the driver you know that
driver is nothing but an implementation
of jdbc apis so this expose jdbc API
expose like okay get me
connection uh insert let's say update
delete but is it actually doing it no
it's just an interface this drivers is
actually has all the implementation how
to get a connection how to insert it how
to update it that from your application
wise you don't have to worry about the
spe specific driver code because you are
dealing with the jdbc apis you do just
get connection your application would do
get connection okay you do update let's
say an update and you provide it it's
it's provided as the interface right now
it's driver which is abstracted to us
how it actually converted to something
which is understand by relational
database we don't have to worry about it
so you don't worry like okay if I'm
using my SQL driver my code will get
changed if I'm using postgress SQL lot
of code changes would be done no nothing
like this you you already got it right
why because we are dealing we are just
invoking that get connection now this
specific driver will take care of
getting the connection so if you change
from my SQL to posts your code will not
change you are still calling get
connection only internal implementation
will change and that's okay so you can
use anything
okay so let's start very basic using JD
jdbc without a spring boot let's say
that if you are not using a spring boot
what how you would make a connection
what are the challenges what that spring
boot resolves actually and once we knows
that then ultimately we move to
jpa so see this class first so very
basic example I have created one public
class database
connection as the class name this is
used to create a connection database
connection so I have created one method
called get
connection okay and it's returning me
the connection
object so now here if you see that the
first step in getting a connection is to
load the driver is to load the driver
into the jvm so when you do class. for
for name and you provide the driver uh
this is the class okay so I am using S2
this one in memory I don't want to
install my SQL and start it server for
testing we can always use S2 and I told
you right doesn't matter like your code
will not change at all either you use my
SQL post or S2 right you are just
calling API jdbc API so the no matter
what first step is you have to load the
driver so I'm using S2 so S2 driver if
you're using MySQL you have to uh load
the MySQL driver so this is the first
step now once the driver is loaded into
the jvm the second step is to establish
a connection with DB okay so here if I
am using there is a class called driver
manager and you do do get connection so
you pass the URL so now here if you see
this URL we are using jdbc yes what is
the uh DB type you're using S2 not my
SQL not post I'm using
S2 even the S2 has two variant like in
memory in memory is like once till your
application is running data is there in
the DB as as soon as your application
shut down data is also gone so it's a
transient data so I'm using memory in
memory like till my application is up
data is there as soon as my application
is shut down uh the data will be lost
there is another variant that you can
even change it to that to process the
data even your application uh shutdown
also so but I am using the transient
flavor of it and this is the DB name
which I want to create so I'm creating a
user DB so when I do get connection and
give the URL if this DB is not there it
will create if it is already there it
will do a connection for that
one okay and username and password so
default username for S2 is essay which
is I think system administrator and mord
is nothing so you need this to get a
connection of your
database okay so first is load a driver
second is establish a connection so this
is two things are present into my
database connection
class now here if you see another class
which I have written user Dow class okay
in this Dow the first method I have like
creating a table
generally understanding is whenever you
are running your application database is
table is already present but since we
are just starting I have also created
one method where I am creating a table
also okay DB is already created here if
not present it will create a DB user DB
so inside this DB it will create a table
one method second method I have written
create user
okay third is uh I have written to read
a user so three methods I have written
so see what happening is like how you
can do that so in this one first thing
whenever you have to query insert update
delete create anything first thing you
need is get a connection of a database
so it creating a new database connection
object so it getting an instance of this
class and then calling the get
connection method it calling this method
what this method does is it will load
the driver it will get one fresh
connection of this
database and provide this connection
once you got the connection then you can
run the query so I have written one
query create table users so I am
creating a users table only with two
column uh three column one is user
ID which is auto
incremented another is usern name and
the third one is
age okay so this is the uh table I am
creating so here whatever the SQL query
string you have created now you just uh
with this statement you just execute
update okay so it will create your table
also notice that there is if any
exception comes you have to handle the
SQL exception and in the final blog you
have to close the resources you have to
close the statement you have to close
the
connection similarly create user
whenever you have to create one user
okay the first step is get the
connection create a new database
connection instance and then call this
method it will give you one connection
database connection then you write your
SQL query which you want to insert into
users username age and user ID is auto
incremented already so no problem in
that so these two values I want to
dynamically insert so I can use prepared
statement okay so connection. prepared
statement you provide this SQL query and
here these two Dynamic values would
be set the values like set a string
first one is a string user name so index
one provide the usern name whatever it
is
coming the second uh the second question
mark is that integer which is age so I'm
doing set in index is two and the age
whatever it is coming and then simply
prepared query execute update so this
will insert one
row okay and similarly you have to catch
the SQL exception and in the finally
block you you have to close the prepared
query and the DB
connection if you see the third method
read query the read users it is also
exactly same so I think now you are
understanding the crust you have to get
the connection then you can use prepared
statement and you can use this prepared
statement uh to run the SQL query so I
run the SQL query select testest from
user so this is the SQL query string so
connection. prepared statement I
provided this SQL query so there is no
Dynamic value so I don't need to set
anything I just run prepared query
execute
query when I run this execute query it
will give me a result set result set is
nothing but a list of rows so I am
iterating and just concatenating just
and printing
it okay so you have to handle the SQL
exception and finally you have to close
it
resources so this is very very basic uh
plain jdbc we are using no spring boot
is used here okay I will show you
running it but what is the problem you
are seeing with this so there are so
many Boiler code we are writing first is
driver class loading you have to load
the driver right class.
forame then you have to make a DB
connection now here if you see you are
doing a data driver manager do get
connection hey give me one connection of
the database and you are providing the
URL username password and this will get
you one connection so you have to
manually get the database connection
third is exception handling so here if
you see what exception you are getting
SQL exception this is very
high level or abstracted exception I
would say so SQL exception can be of
anything uh maybe primary key violation
duplicate key found you are not able to
insert like there are so many different
ways through which your query fails but
it gives a very high level abstracted
error SQL exception so you have to do a
lot of uh kind of if else check okay if
this is the issue then okay do this so
here SQL exception I would say that it's
not very clear okay closing of the DB
connection and other objects like
statement so here if you see that every
time you take out a connection or use a
resource now here you are creating a
prepared statement executing the query
in the finally block you ultimately have
to close the DB connection and close the
prepared query also because if you don't
do that there is a possibility of memory
leak also so as normal jdbc you have to
handle the closing of the DB connection
also and the last one is manual handling
of DB connection pool so here if you see
that currently every time somebody's
calling new instance. get connection I
am creating blindly creating one
connection but it is not an ideal way
generally ideal way would be like okay
there should be one pool of jdbc
connection pool in which already I have
pre-created few connections use it once
use it return it back to the pool so you
have to manually add it or handle it DB
connections pool okay with the
jdbc so these are uh the few issues with
the plain jdbc but before I uh jump to
Spring boot uh jdbc how it handles it
let's see that so the plane jdbc the
same thing I have database connection
class first class uh loader we are
loading it and then we are establishing
a DB
connection and in the user
Dow we are creating a user table
first and then I have also have a create
user method and read user method okay so
every time I use it I uh handle the
exception and also in the finally block
I closed it properly so I have just
written the comment here so just to that
we have to close it here so let's start
the
server okay and here I have a user
controller which is like plain jdbc is
like get user call plain
jdbc so here I am using get user this
I'm hitting this get API okay uh so this
get API just for testing purpose you can
say that don't go with like why in the
get why we are doing a create and this
one so this is just for testing purpose
that my control comes here so once the
controls will come here so let me put a
debugger
Point let me start in a debug
mode so here once the control comes here
so what happen is I am creating a user
do object now I am creating two users X
and Y so I am creating X and Y and then
ultimately I'm doing read user so in the
read user the same thing I told you
right first get an object of the
connection and your query and you can
use prepared query to run this execute
query and you can iterate it to print it
here so I am iterated it and
return so success is printed and if you
see the console
log the two rows got printed this is the
user ID which is Auto incremented 1 and
two this is the usern name and this is
the age okay so this is currently in
memory now spring boot helps to remove
all this Boiler code for
us so now let's see using jdbc with the
spring boot so the first thing you have
to do is include the dependency in
pom.xml
so this is spring boot stter
jdbc okay so this is for uh jdbc
interfaces and all it will bring and the
second dependency you need for this S2
S2 database we are using right in memory
one so this is for the database you can
replace it with u uh MySQL or post
address whichever you like So currently
I'm using inmemory S2 so I'm uh added
its
dependency okay so spring boot provide
jdbc
template class which helps to remove all
the Boiler code which we see at top how
now let's see that once you have added
the dependency now let's see this
example so now here if you see first I
have created one basic pojo of
user user ID username age and it's
getter and Setter very Basics user class
now the second I have created user
repository class I have given a name
user repository class and annotate with
at theate
repository it work as at theate
component
so it will help us to create a bean of
user repository and also help us in the
scanning of those Bean like what adorate
component
does the second is is that at the top in
the plain jdbc you see SQL exception
comes right but here this repository
whenever spring boot see that okay it is
annotated with at theate repository any
SQL exception comes it gives a granual
level of
exception okay we'll see
how
so after creating this user class pojo
class I am creating a user repository
annotated with atate repository and here
if you see that I have added a
dependency in this one of jdbc template
this is the class which I'm talking
about which help us to remove all the
Boiler code so jdbc template I have Auto
wired it okay so Bean will get inserted
into
it so here I have also have the same
methods I written one is create one is
insert and another is read three method
same like above so create table now here
if you see jdbc template execute okay
and you can directly write your query in
the execute you can directly write your
plain SQL query
itself in the insert jdbc template do
update you provide your insert query now
if your insert query is need to be like
certain values which need to be
dynamically feed it can be added like
this there are different methods I will
tell you don't go inside like how this
update is used I will tell you what are
the different ways but currently
understand this like you are just
calling the method jdbc template. update
put the query and all the values which
has to be goes into this
field and similarly get users what I
doing is I have returned the query I am
doing just jdbc template. query and
given the query now here I'm just uh
iterating over the result set I
go later into deep what I am doing
it now the difference you might be
seeing that I am not creating DB
connection
here okay I am not written any finally
block where I'm closing the DB
connection or closing the prepared
statement anything nothing all I am
using is just uh jdbc template execute
just for executing the plane query there
is something like update where for more
more complex queries where you have to
dynamically fill the values and it also
provide for read like do query where
which is used for fetching the
data so this is your second class which
you have to create and here if you
see the service class which uses this
actually this is more of a helper class
I would say that this is your
business logic class
okay so this is I have annotated with at
theate component you can also annotate
it with at theate service okay so I have
autowired this user
repository
okay
now anybody wants to create a table they
will invoke this and ultimately it will
call user repository create table insert
user this will ultimately go and call
this method get user ultimate this and
call this method it will get the list
currently I'm doing my business logic is
I'm just simply system do do do print
and I'm writing and simply return the
user okay so this class is nothing but a
user service class is nothing but which
is calling the repository class okay and
it is your business logic class like
after fetching the data from the DB any
business logic you have to perform you
can perform here at this Lev
level and the last is you have to use an
application. properties now here if you
see that we are providing certain
properties data source property like I'm
providing the
URL so now here if you see at the top
plane
jdbc you are providing the uh you are
doing a connection and then providing a
URL username password driver link all
you have to do here is in the
springboard is in the this application.
properties you provide what is the URL
the same thing this is your DB I am
using memory version of H2 and
jdbc the driver username password
okay so now this data source this data
source
object data source object in Spring boot
helps with two things one
is database
connection it creates a
connection returns it manage it and also
it helps with the connection pooling
connection
pool okay it manage the connection pool
so this data source object so internally
spring boot help us to do whatever we
were doing class do for name okay then
do create a connection and everything is
spring boot does it and surprisingly I
will tell you spring boot also by
default provide us a connection pool
also it is
Hikari CP connection pool Hikari
connection pool I will show you the demo
but
before uh going proceed further is this
clear like how it is helping us
resolving it so here if you see driver
class loading are we doing anywhere
driver class loading no we are not in
the spring boot jdbc we are not doing
class. for name and the driver path we
are not doing anywhere this is just a
business logic class so here if you see
we are just directly using
repository and application. properties
we are not doing driver class so jdbc
template loaded at the time of
application startup in driver manager
class let's see
that so now let's see the
driver manager class and I'm just
starting an application so driver
manager what we are saying is jdbc
loaded at the time of application
startup itself so now I'm starting the
application in a debug mode now here if
you see during application startup
itself it is doing class. for name for
us earlier we used to do in the plain
jdbc now it is doing it okay and here if
you see that it has the data which we
provided all. as2 driver in the
application. properties okay so one
thing is driver class loading is now get
abstracted from us jdbc template does
it database connection making now you
can ask here in this when is the
database connection happening happen
whenever we run any particular query
through jdbc template like like do
update do query at that point of time it
tried to create create a corre
connection okay so connection making
from the either it has to make a new
connection it will create that time or
it has to take from the pool it will do
that time itself now let's say that
insert user I am trying to insert so if
you go inside this
update
update this method it do execute if you
go inside
this it do this data source utils get
connection
okay so if you go inside this it will
actually handles like the connection
making do get connection from the data
source okay exception handling so
exception in plain jdbc we get very
abstracted SQL exception but in jdbc
template we get granual error like
duplicate key exception query timeout
exception so if you go this package a.
springf framework. Dow package so let's
see that package here if we see this
package Dow on do spring framework. Dow
package these are the different type of
exception it provide cannot acquire lock
exception data access exception data in
Integrity violation exception duplicate
key exception empty results exception so
there are different type of exceptions
can and come query timeout exception so
all this jdbc template do mapping
internally from instead of just throwing
SQL exception it throws a granual level
of exception and through spring boot in
the previous video I have already told
you how you can handle a exception of
any particular type okay but you get
some granual level exception and you can
handle it properly it is not very like
abstraction SQL exception happen what we
don't
know closing of the DB connection and
other resources now again you can ask me
sh like in the spring boot jdbc we are
just using J jdbc template to execute
the query okay plane query update but
where are we closing it again that is
handled by your jdbc template itself now
let's goes
to uh here let's say jdbc template.
update I trying to insert right if you
go inside
this in the finally block it do cleanup
parameters okay okay so here it has a
proper knowledge that whether I have to
close the connection or whether I have
to put it back into the pool okay so you
don't have to handle it that is also
handled by your jdbc
itself and the last thing is herey sh
what about the DB connection pool still
here I do not see where we are writing
the connection pool logic like in a
connection pool I have only this
uh five
jdbc connection pool and only this five
would be
used who is doing that so here if you
see when you have defined this
application. properties in data source
okay
so means you are relying on Spring boot
that
hey you use the data
source see data source object right it
helps you to connect to the database and
helps to manage connection pool but here
we just provided like what is the driver
what is the URL username password we
didn't tell like what data source we
want to use there are different data
sources which we can use but here we
haven't told it so spring board use by
default Hikari data source and Hikari
data source also provide Hikari
connection
pool so now here if you
see Hikari provide default jdbc
connection pool that is Hikari CP
connection pool with minimum and maximum
pool size of
10 and we can change the configuration
in application. properties so in
application do properties you can put
like spring. data source s Hikari
maximum pool is 10 and the minimum is
five by default is 10 10 so here if you
see we can check like uh how it is
making a connection so uh Hikari data
source whenever it will do get
connection let's see
that okay so hiari data source it
came so here if you see Hikari pool it
is using
connection time out idle time out
maximum maximum pool size 10 minimum is
10 okay so spring boot act this Hikari
is actually very efficient and it's very
fast actually and no matter if you're
using SQL postgress or S2 spring boot by
default uses this only this data source
only but if you want to use any other
specific uh jdbc connection pool you
don't want to use Hikari you don't you
have you want to use some other one
right uh maybe some from Apache or some
uh something some other jdbc connection
pool then instead of putting into the
application. properties you don't have
to put into application. properties then
you can in your configuration at theate
configuration class app config class you
can create a
bean of data source and then you can use
whichever data source you want here in
this for example I'm using the same Ki
data source only okay uh but you can
change it to any other jdbc connection
pool which is available and you can use
it on your own so here driver class name
jdb instead of now application.
properties I am providing the
configuration for the data source like
this jdbc pool username password like
this okay now here I don't need to
provide uh in the application.
properties now this data source would be
used currently here I am using Hikari
only but you can use any you can replace
it with anything
okay and uh yeah we can show the
complete demo
here so here if you see that let's see
this I'm calling this API jdbc okay
first it will do create
table user table is
created if it's not then user one is
added user is
added and after that what it is doing is
we are doing get user so we are using
user service.
getuser and this get user uh service
layer calls repository it do get users
so ultimately what are how many users we
created two so I got a list of two users
and I'm iterating it and printing
it so two times it printed and ultimate
Ely it returns list of user itself
finished so here if you see two users it
returns and also I was printing it so
two users got
printed okay jdbc template in Spring
boot has couple of methods very
frequently used method I will tell you
one is
update and it takes two parameter one is
SQL a string and another is where where
AR variable arguments okay so this
update method can be used for insert
update and delete
operation so like
this insert into user so I have written
my SQL query as an string and two
Dynamic values which I need to insert
okay so this is my string now I'm using
jdbc template. update your query and
second is variable arguments like
variable arguments 1 2 3 could be
anything right so two Dynamic right so
one is your string second is your
integer this
one okay similarly it can be used for
update so this is one method very very
commonly used method of jdbc
template another is this one for
updating
update the same your query and the
second is prepared statement Setter PSS
you can say it is also you can use for
insert update delete it is just for like
more granual level or you can say that
more if your queries are very very
complex then prepared statement Setter
is can be
useful the similar first thing is insert
query like you can write your string
okay uh you have to set Dynamic values
now I'm instead of uh using the previous
I'm now using prepared statement Setter
jdbc template. update the first
parameter is your string query
now second is prepared statement Setter
so here if you see uh
jdbc
template update string
SQL so yeah this prepared statement
Setter here if you see it is a
functional interface okay so you can use
Lambda expression and it has only one
method which need to be
implemented okay so one
method which accept prepared statement
so
that's why I'm using Lambda expression
in Java playlist I've already explained
it in depth how you can use Lambda
expression so here I am just providing
the implementation for that get values
itself that whatever the prepared
statement set the string the first one
is a string username so for the first
index it's a string second Index this
one
second is integer right so I'm providing
H so this is fun to this is our index
1 2 3 4 right so this is one this is two
another question mark this would be
three so this way you can add it okay so
you can use it for insert update delete
these are the two ways
similarly now you have to fetch it right
so one is
query query method it takes one flavor
is it takes two parameter one is a
string which is your SQL query second is
row mapper now it is used to F get
multip mle rows you have to F multiple
rows so now here if you see this query
the jdbc template. query the first one
is your select query a string and the
second one is
your row mapper so this row mapper is a
functional interface which has one
method map Pro which takes two
parameters so that's why this two
parameters and whenever this method get
invoked this map
Pro this is the implementation should
run okay so see that what might be
happening inside so in the user
repository when I am doing get users
let's see it might be doing
query it going inside
query uh
here execute
query after it executed the query it got
a result set so result set can be like
10 rows 20 rows then it has to extract
data out of
it row mapper now it is here if you see
it is iterating over this each row set
each row and calling the map row okay so
now this will get executed for each row
Set uh there are total five rows then
for each row I am creating a user object
and do a mapping like in the row this
column row. get in user ID so I'm
putting into this user ID field it's
just a mapping between a column and the
object user object so row set. getet
string is like username I putting into
username like this and ultimately it
will return a list it will just keep on
adding into the result list and
ultimately return this list of
user the second flavor is query for list
again first parameter is a St and second
is class the purpose is to get single
column of multiple rows single column of
multiple rows so here jdbc template.
query for list provide the
query select username from users if
there are total 10 users you will get
username for all the 10 users only so
one column whenever you want to fet the
one specific column for multiple rows
then go ahead use this query for list
okay so the second parameter is class
type so this username is a string docl
class okay so here if you see query for
list and we can search for here query
for list what it does get single column
row mapper so it is a single column it's
uh mapping is based on single column
like a single type a
string then the third query could be
like query for object the first is your
SQL query then arguments and the
required type get single row this is
used for fetching a single row so jdbc
template that query for object the first
is your SQL query select estess from
user where user ID equals to it could be
dynamic so that's where your second
parameter comes into the picture object
array
so I'm creating an object array only one
right in the array so I'm putting like
it should be replaced with one if there
are more question mark you can just put
into arrays it will sequentially it will
update the question mark so it will
change user ID equals to one with this
and the third one is required type is
the object in which this row has to be
mapped to so I want to map to the user
so internally it will do mapping use
make use of getter and Setters of user
and it will map this each column of this
row into this user
object and the last is like query for
object SQL and required type get only
single value it is used for get only
single value like jdpc template get
query for object select count asress
from user you do integer do class so now
here if you see it return only one
single value so if you have any
requirement where you get only one
single value then you can use this get
for object so these are generally
different flavors which uh jdbc template
provides which you can do to insert
update delete or fetch the
data
okay so but with this I hope that at
least this
jdbc and this driver part should be
properly clear where this exactly comes
into the picture how you can connect to
the
DV what all problems are there in the
plane gdbc what spring boot jdbc
resolves it and how it resolve
it because then only it makes sense to
understand om framework and jpn
hibernate okay so next we will start
with the orm object relational mapping
but we'll see you in the part two but if
the part one if you have any doubts
let's discuss in the comment section
thank you bye okay